<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: iPhone | DataChomp]]></title>
  <link href="http://datachomp.github.com/blog/categories/iphone/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://datachomp.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-08T14:33:18-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://datachomp.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rob Sullivan]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[rob@datachomp.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Change iPhone root password after jailbreak]]></title>
    <link href="http://datachomp.github.com/archives/change-iphone-root-password-after-jailbreak/"/>
    <updated>2010-07-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://datachomp.github.com/archives/change-iphone-root-password-after-jailbreak</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>One of the great benefits to having a jailbroken iPhone is the SSH feature. One of the great security risks of having a jailbroken iPhone is the SSH feature and the fact that the phone has the same global password for all iPhones. Luckily, there is a quick fix for this.</p>

<p>In Cydia, go to the "Search" section and find the app called <strong><em>MobileTerminal</em></strong>. Install it, then launch it.<br/>
From there, type in <strong><em>su root</em></strong> and hit return. This changes us to the root user so we can access/change the password for it. It will then prompt you to type in that global root password of <strong><em>alpine</em></strong> . Once you are root, just type <strong><em>passwd</em></strong> then hit return. From there, you will need to enter, then re-enter your password and the change should take place. Simply type in <strong><em>exit</em></strong> to leave the root account and get back to the standard prompt.</p>

<p><strong>Another Notch: Changing the Mobile User</strong><br/>
You should also consider doing the same thing for your Mobile user as it uses a global password of "alpine" as well<br/>
You start the MobileTerminal app as the Mobile user, so to change the password for it simply type <strong>*passwd</strong> Then type alpine when it prompts, then fill out the stuff for the new password and start sleeping better at night knowing that you have just put up a basic security fence for your sweet sweet jailbroken phone.
For more information, check out these handy posts:</p>

<p>and</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
