<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: MVC | DataChomp]]></title>
  <link href="http://datachomp.com/blog/categories/mvc/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://datachomp.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-08T23:12:33-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://datachomp.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rob Sullivan]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[rob@datachomp.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CI with MVC4 and Linux? No Problem]]></title>
    <link href="http://datachomp.com/archives/ci-with-mvc4-and-linux-no-problem/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://datachomp.com/archives/ci-with-mvc4-and-linux-no-problem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>There are a lot of tools out there that we can use to automate our awesomeness. One of those easy/free/fun tools is a continuous integration (CI) server. Since we are building in Windows and deploying to Linux, we can go ahead and upgrade a CI server from &lsquo;important&rsquo; to essential. There are various products out there that can accomplish this; I&rsquo;m going with what I know and that is <a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/teamcity/" title="TeamCity">TeamCity</a> from JetBrains.</p>

<p>On our Ubuntu box, after we finish the easy as candy install, we&rsquo;re going to want to install Mono. Check out <a href="http://datachomp.com/archives/running-asp-net-mvc4-on-ubuntu-12-04/" title="Install Mono on Ubuntu">this previous post</a> on how to do that and set it up in your /etc/environment.</p>

<p>Now that Mono is rocking, lets hop over to our CI install. At the time of this post, the latest version of TeamCity is 7.0.2a. Looking at the code below, we&rsquo;re going to install Java, pull down the latest version of the TeamCity linux tar, decompress it, switch directories and fire it up :<br/>
<code></p>

<pre><code>sudo apt-get install openjdk-7-jre
wget - http://download.jetbrains.com/teamcity/TeamCity-7.0.2a.tar.gz
tar xfz TeamCity-7.0.2a.tar.gz
cd Teamcity
sudo ./bin/runAll.bat start
</code></pre>

<p></code></p>

<p>Pretty easy right? Lets check out our web interface:<a href="http://files.datachomp.com/AppDev/mono/teamcitywelcome.png"><img src="http://files.datachomp.com/AppDev/mono/teamcitywelcome.png" alt="TeamcityWelcome" /></a></p>

<p>Yay! Everything works! You&rsquo;re also at a ubiquitous web interface which will likely give the Softie in you some solace. There are tons of resources online for setting up your project in TeamCity to check it out, build it, run tests, deploy, yada yada yada. If you are just getting started, I highly recommend <a href="http://www.troyhunt.com/2010/11/you-deploying-it-wrong-teamcity.html" title="Troy Hunt Deployments">Troy Hunt&rsquo;s post.</a> You can also install Ruby on this server and have a wonderfully awesome auto-deployment method via <a href="https://github.com/capistrano/capistrano/wiki/Documentation-v2.x" title="Capistrano">Capistrano</a>. If you are interested in deploying with Capistrano, let me know I&rsquo;ll try to barf out a quick post on it. This is a pretty short and to the point post, if it needs more content with regards to project checkouts and stuff, let me know and I can barf that out as well.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Running ASP.NET MVC4 on Ubuntu 12.04]]></title>
    <link href="http://datachomp.com/archives/running-asp-net-mvc4-on-ubuntu-12-04/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://datachomp.com/archives/running-asp-net-mvc4-on-ubuntu-12-04</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>The single most question I get regarding our <a href="http://tekpub.com/productions/pg" title="Hello Postgres">Hello Postgres</a> series over Tekpub is &ldquo;How are you running your app on Linux?&rdquo; As much as I enjoy sending volleys of fragmented explanations over emails to people, I decided it might be in everyone&rsquo;s best interest if I just blog it out. Technology moves fast&hellip; like super fast. So instead of showing you how to deploy an old and busted MVC3 app to a &ldquo;has been&rdquo; Ubuntu 11.10, we&rsquo;re going to be going with MVC4 and <a href="https://wiki.ubuntu.com/PrecisePangolin/TechnicalOverview/Beta2" title="Ubuntu 12.04 beta 2">Ubuntu 12.04</a>. We&rsquo;re so bleeding edge you can call us cutters!</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not going to show you how to set up and install your Ubuntu Server, as there is a ton of internet out there that can handle that for you and the installer itself is pretty hard to mess up. What I will cover is what to do after that last reboot where it is just you and Bash, together&hellip; at last.</p>

<p>SSH into your fancy new Ubuntu box with <a href="http://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/putty/" title="Putty">Putty</a> and Run this:<br/>
<code>sudo apt-get update &amp;&amp; sudo apt-get -y install git-core curl python-software-properties</code></p>

<p>This is going to let us add the ppa(think of this as a package location) to install a current nginx:<br/>
<code></p>

<pre><code>sudo add-apt-repository ppa:nginx/stable
sudo apt-get update &amp;&amp; sudo apt-get -y install nginx
</code></pre>

<p></code></p>

<p>Yes! We can now git things, we can curl things, and we can nginx things! Rawwrr!!! Let&rsquo;s kick some other processes to the curb&hellip; like that skank MySQL and that wet blanket Apache:<br/>
<code>sudo update-rc.d mysql remove &amp;&amp;<br/>
sudo update-rc.d apache2 remove &amp;&amp; mkdir mycoolapp</code></p>

<p>Now for the fun part, let&rsquo;s get Mono up and running. We really want the latest version of Mono, and like Nuget, not all packages in Ubuntu stay current. The fix for this in the mono world is to just grab <a href="http://www.integratedwebsystems.com/2012/04/install-mono-2-11/" title="Nathan Bridgewater">this dudes</a> install script and go have a drink because it takes a bit to finish:<br/>
<code></p>

<pre><code>mkdir mono-2.11
cd mono-2.11
wget --no-check-certificate https://github.com/nathanb/iws-snippets/raw/master/mono-install-scripts/ubuntu/install_mono-2.11.sh
chmod 755 install_mono-2.11.sh
./install_mono-2.11.sh
</code></pre>

<p></code></p>

<p>Now to check that we have the current version, we just run the following:<br/>
<code>/opt/mono-2.11/bin/mono -V</code></p>

<p>Cool! We&rsquo;re current, but what we really need is to just be able to run &ldquo;mono -V&rdquo; anywhere we want. We can do that by modifying our /etc/environment file:<br/>
<code>sudo nano /etc/environment</code></p>

<h1>then insert &ldquo;:/opt/mono-2.11/bin&rdquo;  at the end of that path string. Log out, log in for it to take effect.`</h1>

<p>I don&rsquo;t now about you, but all this sys-admin crap is putting me to sleep and I want to code. Back on our Widows/Dev box, we&rsquo;re going to new up an empty MVC4 project (up to you to figure out how to get MVC4 going on your box, I used Web Platform Installer). After the project is new'ed up:</p>

<ul>
<li>Add a controller</li>
<li>Add a view based on that controller</li>
<li>Hit F5 and make sure it works</li>
<li>Remove the EntityFramework.dll because we love our data and don&rsquo;t want to give our app a low self esteem</li>
<li>Once removed, hit F5 again</li>
</ul>


<p>If everything is still running, then do a file system deploy to a local folder of your choice. Go check out what was just deployed, specifically the &lsquo;/bin&rsquo; folder. We want to remove the Web.Infrastructure.dll because Mono already has this built into its GAC. High Five Mono! With that out of the way, we are going to copy that deployment over to the &lsquo;mycoolapp&rsquo; folder on our Linux server using <a href="http://winscp.net/eng/index.php" title="Winscp">WinsCP</a>. While I don&rsquo;t have a WordPress plugin to read your mind, I hear you thinking &ldquo;Rob, surely there are better ways to do this.&rdquo; and you are right. However, this post is long enough and that topic will likely go into its own post.</p>

<p>SSH back into your linux box, and &lsquo;cd mycoolapp&rsquo;. &ldquo;cd&rdquo; into your &ldquo;mycoolapp&rdquo; directory, type in &lsquo;ls&rsquo; to see the contents and make sure your app made it over. Once we see it, we can do a cassini like run of it by typeing out xsp4 and hitting enter. Try and hit your box on the port 8080 (xsp4 should tell you what it is running on) and see if you can see your app:</p>

<p><img src="http://files.datachomp.com/AppDev/mono/monoapp.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Yay! Our code works and we&rsquo;re so open source now that we can wear tight jeans at Starbucks and put Bon Iver on our ipod&hellip; just like those <a href="http://wekeroad.com/" title="Lead Rails Wanker">Rails wankers</a>! As for nginx and running our site as a Mono service, we can just use some of the nice documentation over at the Mono site:</p>

<p>Nginx config:<br/>
<a href="http://www.mono-project.com/FastCGI_Nginx" title="FastCGI_Nginx">http://www.mono-project.com/FastCGI_Nginx</a></p>

<p>Mono as a service:<br/>
<a href="http://yojimbo87.github.com/2010/03/14/mono-startup-script.html" title="Monoserve">http://yojimbo87.github.com/2010/03/14/mono-startup-script.html</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting started with Postgres and MVC3]]></title>
    <link href="http://datachomp.com/archives/getting-started-with-postgres-and-mvc3/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-20T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://datachomp.com/archives/getting-started-with-postgres-and-mvc3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>&ldquo;<strong><em><a href="http://www.postgresql.org/">Postgres</a>? WTF man, you&rsquo;re a SQL Server DBA!</em></strong>&rdquo; It&rsquo;s true, I am a SQL Server DBA but even I have to admit that the Postgres team is doing some <a href="http://www.postgresql.org/about/featurematrix">wildy exciting stuff</a>. With that in mind, lets take a quick look at just how quickly we can replace SQL Server with a free/open full bore Enterprise database system like <a href="http://www.postgresql.org/">Postgres</a>.</p>

<p>One of the first things you will notice is Postgres is way easier to install than SQL Server. The SQL Server install is born from a truck stop romance between TFS and Sharepoint that someone found in a garbage bag in a dumpster and burned to a DVD. Postgres takes a different angle and opts for a &lsquo;less is more&rsquo; type of approach. One of the big things you will want to pay attention to is the password you give the default &lsquo;postgres&rsquo; account. Think of him as the SA account in SQL Server as he too wields a mighty big stick.</p>

<p>Once we finish the installer, lets open up pgAdmin III (henceforth known as pgAdmin). If you are accustomed to SSMS with SQL Server and always wished it went on a diet&hellip; then you might like pgAdmin. Be warned though, pgAdmin isn&rsquo;t SSMS on a diet&hellip; it is like SSMS with Anorexia. Once pgAdmin is opened and you are connected, then drill down to &lsquo;databases&rsquo; and do a &lsquo;new database&rsquo; and use the GUI to make your fancy new demo database, or just run the raw sql:</p>

<pre><code>1.  &amp;nbsp;

2.  CREATE DATABASE "Demo"

3.    WITH ENCODING='UTF8'

4.         OWNER=postgres

5.         CONNECTION LIMIT=-1;

6.  &amp;nbsp;
</code></pre>

<p>Next, lets hop in that database and throw up some tables/data:</p>

<pre><code>1.  &amp;nbsp;

2.  CREATE TABLE "Colors"

3.  &amp;#40;

4.      colorid serial NOT NULL,

5.      colorname character varying&amp;#40;50&amp;#41; NOT NULL,

6.      constraint pk_colorid PRIMARY KEY &amp;#40;colorid&amp;#41;

7.  &amp;#41;

8.  WITH &amp;#40;OIDS=false&amp;#41;;

9.  &amp;nbsp;

10. INSERT INTO "Colors" &amp;#40;colorname&amp;#41;

11. VALUES &amp;#40;'red'&amp;#41;;

12. INSERT INTO "Colors" &amp;#40;colorname&amp;#41;

13. VALUES &amp;#40;'blue'&amp;#41;;

14. SELECT * FROM "Colors";

15. &amp;nbsp;
</code></pre>

<p>So why the quotes around the table names you might be asking&hellip; well, SQL Server has a bit of Honey Badger approach to what case you assign names and Postgres treats it like a pretty big deal. Luckily, overcoming it isn&rsquo;t a big deal, we just double quote it. Now, if you don&rsquo;t have years of tsql or <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CamelCase">camelcasing</a> drilled into your brain, you can easy just do everything in lower case and not fight the double quote dragon.<br/>
What else sticks out there&hellip; oh Data Types! You will have to adjust to some variance in data types, but in a good way. Postgres has a lavish assortment of data types for you to fall in love with and one of which is using &lsquo;serial&rsquo; instead of the whole IDENTITY(1,1) you might be used to in SQL Server. There are also some really cool things called Sequences in Postgres which are blazing fast and give you the value of the ID before you insert it. DBAs like them because it can get you AppDevs away from fatty GUID primary keys.</p>

<p>Fire up a new MVC3 app and hop into the Nuget console. From there, we&rsquo;re going to add our <a href="http://www.nuget.org/List/Packages/Npgsql">Postgre provider</a> with &ldquo;<strong>Install-Package Npgsql</strong>&rdquo;. Now that we have our vital provider assemblies, lets go mess around in the web.config.</p>

<pre><code>1.  &amp;nbsp;

2.  

3.      

4.          

5.              

10.         

11.     

12. &amp;nbsp;

13.     

14.         

15.     

16. &amp;nbsp;
</code></pre>

<p>Yeah! We have our provider factory rocking and our connection string. Yes, I am using the postgres account in this demo and yes that is wrong/stupid, but I&rsquo;m having so much fun playing with the Postgres engine that I decided to take a shortcut there for this entry.</p>

<p>So our color app is pretty quick and dirty. In keeping with that spirit, I&rsquo;m going to use <a href="https://github.com/robconery/massive">Massive</a> as my ORM of choice. It already has a <a href="https://github.com/robconery/massive/blob/master/Massive.PostgreSQL.cs">Postgres version</a> ready to go. <a href="https://github.com/toptensoftware/petapoco">PetaPoco</a> has some very nice Postgres options in it, but Massive is very quick/easy and the Expandos makes all the strong-typers uncomfortable and I love a good code-trolling.</p>

<p>In the Model folder of our app, I create a new class file called Massive and I copy/paste the <a href="https://github.com/robconery/massive/blob/master/Massive.PostgreSQL.cs">Postgres version</a> into it, and I also created a new class file called &ldquo;Colors&rdquo; that I pasted the following in:</p>

<pre><code>1.  &amp;nbsp;

2.      public class Color : DynamicModel

3.      &amp;#123;

4.          public Color&amp;#40;&amp;#41; : base&amp;#40;"pg", "Colors", "colorid"&amp;#41; &amp;#123; &amp;#125;

5.  &amp;nbsp;

6.      &amp;#125;

7.  &amp;nbsp;
</code></pre>

<p>All wired up! In the home controller, we&rsquo;ll throw some code to play with our table in:</p>

<pre><code>1.  &amp;nbsp;

2.  var table = [new][8] Color&amp;#40;&amp;#41;;

3.  var colors = table.All&amp;#40;&amp;#41;;

4.  ViewBag.colors = colors;

5.  &amp;nbsp;
</code></pre>

<p>And then in our view:</p>

<pre><code>1.  &amp;nbsp;

2.  @foreach &amp;#40;var color in ViewBag.colors&amp;#41;

3.  &amp;#123; 

4.       @: @color.colorid @color.colorname

5.  &amp;#125;

6.  &amp;nbsp;
</code></pre>

<p>F5 and what do we get? BOOM!!! &ldquo;Error 42P01: relation "colors&rdquo; does not exist"<br/>
So remember when I started our Colors table with a capital C? This is where it can come back to bite you&hellip; and also one of the reasons I absolutely love Micro-ORMs. Fast, malleable, and so easy a DBA can use it. Let&rsquo;s hop into Massive and throw some quotes around our table access:</p>

<pre><code>1.  &amp;nbsp;

2.  string sql = limit &gt;  ? "SELECT TOP "   limit   " {0} FROM "&amp;#123;1&amp;#125;" " : "SELECT {0} FROM "&amp;#123;1&amp;#125;" ";

3.  &amp;nbsp;
</code></pre>

<p>and Viola! It works! In pretty much the time it takes to install SQL Server, we&rsquo;re already rocking our stunning and highly valuable colors app!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tekpub &#8211; Full Throttle with Rob Sullivan show notes]]></title>
    <link href="http://datachomp.com/archives/tekpub-full-throttle-with-rob-sullivan-show-notes/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://datachomp.com/archives/tekpub-full-throttle-with-rob-sullivan-show-notes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>The question emails are starting to pile in (which is a good thing!) so this post is basically a way to centralize links/answers. In the show, I say a few times &ldquo;we&rsquo;ll see this later&rdquo; (like with SQL Server Profiler) and we never see it&hellip; that was mostly my fault. For some reason I kept thinking I would be able to squeeze 5 hours of content into 1 hour and was wrong. If there are aspects of SQL Server that you would like to see more of, as well as real world problems that you may have and would like to see solutions to, then let <a href="http://help.tekpub.com/">Tekpub know</a>. We&rsquo;ll see if we can hack out real world solutions wrapped in a warm blanket of statistics and opinion.</p>

<p><strong>Questions:</strong>*<br/>
<strong>How do you get the stats to appear in the &ldquo;messages&rdquo; window?</strong><br/>
Those stats come from the following commands:<br/>
SET STATISTICS IO ON;<br/>
SET STATISTICS TIME ON;<br/>
If you don&rsquo;t want to turn it on for every query/window, you can do what I do and set them to always be on in Management studio, you can do this by :<br/>
Tools &ndash;> Options &ndash;> Query Execution &ndash;> SQL Server &ndash;> Advanced<br/>
then check:<br/>
SET STATISTICS IO ON;<br/>
SET STATISTICS TIME ON;
<strong>Lock Pages in Memory, is that always good?</strong><br/>
No, and perhaps I glossed over that section too much or technology changes too fast. While Lock Pages in Memory can be a wonderful setting, there are of course times when it can be pretty bad. You can read more about that here: <a href="http://sqlserverperformance.wordpress.com/2011/02/14/sql-server-and-the-lock-pages-in-memory-right-in-windows-server/">http://sqlserverperformance.wordpress.com/2011/02/14/sql-server-and-the-lock-pages-in-memory-right-in-windows-server/</a>
<strong>Why no filtered index on Posts?</strong><br/>
In our first scenario, to get the front page up&hellip; we just went with the index that the engine suggested.. That got us up and running which is great, but there is room for improvement. To me, filtered indexes are more of a business rule decision and with enough time, if we saw that the load was heavy and predictable enough, we would have likely thrown a filtered index to satisfy the front page query.</p>

<p><strong>What were you using for &ldquo;Intellisense&rdquo; in management studio?</strong> I am not extremely big on intellisense in general, however, I am kind of big on formatting and having a variety of administrative snippets at my finger tips. I use a 3rd party tool called Red-Gate SQL Prompt and have it moderately customized. Keep in mind, I really only use this type of product on data sets I am not very familiar with like the one in this demo. On datasets that I know pretty well, I find intellisense to really just get in the way and make me angry.</p>

<p><strong>And the database?</strong> I am still working on a way to make the DB available. It is roughly 40GB raw, and 4GB compressed. If having the data is a big deal to you, hit me up on email and we can work something out (S3,FTP, yada yada yada)</p>

<p><strong>Tech used in the series:</strong><br/>
Visual Studio 2010 / MVC3 / EF 4.1<br/>
SQL Server 2008 R2 / Management Studio<br/>
<a href="http://www.red-gate.com/products/sql-development/sql-prompt/">Red Gate SQL Prompt</a> &ldquo;Intellisense&rdquo; and &ldquo;snippets&rdquo; in Management Studio<br/>
<a href="http://www.sqlsentry.com/plan-explorer/sql-server-query-view.asp">SQL Sentry Plan Explorer</a> The fun/effective way to view execution plans<br/>
<a href="http://efprof.com/">EF Profiler</a> The SQL Server friendly way to profile EF<br/>
<a href="http://www.cpuid.com/softwares/cpu-z.html">CPU-Z</a> A tried and true hardware enthusiasts way of checking hardware specs.</p>

<p><strong>Source code:</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Massive and using multiple args:]]></title>
    <link href="http://datachomp.com/archives/massive-and-using-multiple-args/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://datachomp.com/archives/massive-and-using-multiple-args</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>So, in <a href="http://blog.wekeroad.com/helpy-stuff/and-i-shall-call-it-massive">Rob Conery&rsquo;s example</a> of using multiple args in a query</p>

<p><code></p>

<pre><code>var tbl = new Products();
var products = tbl.All(where: "CategoryID = @0 AND UnitPrice &gt; @1", orderBy: "ProductName", limit: 20, args: 5,20);
</code></pre>

<p></code>
It makes the args appear to be this completely bad ass and intelligent command that knows exactly when and where to parse/apply the values. Well, in the real world versions of Massive the compiler doesn&rsquo;t take to kindly to that sort of syntax.</p>

<p>args: is a parameter of type object [] so the way I use multiple params is as follows:
<code></p>

<pre><code>object[] queryargs = {"Okapi", "online"};
var DBBasics = table.All(where: "WHERE ServerName=@0 and status = @1", args: queryargs );
</code></pre>

<p></code>
and low and behold the magic happens.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
